Guide to the Records of Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local 137 WAG.180
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local 137 Records
1916; circa 1950s-1991; undated
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sheet Metal Workers' International Association. Local 137
WAG.180
12 Linear Feet in 12 record cartons, one folder, and one oversize folder
Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local 137 is the Greater New York, Long Island, Westchester and Rockland local union of the International Association of Sheet Metal, Air, Rail, and Transportation Workers. Most of its members' work is fabricating, rigging, and installing metal signboards. This has included production of many of the electric signs on Broadway's "Great White Way," the time ball used at New Year's Eve celebrations at Times Square, as well as signs for suburban shopping centers. Its charter was issued in 1924, but the Local was founded earlier, possibly as early as 1911. The Collection includes correspondence, Executive Board minutes, apprenticeship records, contracts, and a small number of photographs, mainly from the 1970s and 1980s.
Scope and Content Note
The records include correspondence, Executive Board minutes, apprenticeship records, contracts, and a small number of photographs, mainly from the 1970s and 1980s.
Related Archival Materials
Morris Rosen Papers (TAM 078)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local 137, in February 2000. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2000.014 and 2000.015.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local 137 is the Greater New York, Long Island, Westchester and Rockland local union of the International Association of Sheet Metal, Air, Rail, and Transportation Workers. Its charter was issued in 1924, as part of what was then the Amalgamated Sheet Metal Workers' International Alliance, but the Local was founded earlier, possibly as early as 1911. Local 137 originally organized workers doing custom automobile body work, but most of its members soon shifted to the skilled work of fabricating and erecting metal signboards (although portion also have worked in production shops making stove tops, electric metal components, and lockers). In collaboration with members of New York City area electricians' and painters' union locals, Local 137 employees fabricated many of the electric and neon signs on Broadway's "Great White Way," and as well as (as employees of of ArtKraft Strauss, one of the premiere sign-making companies in the United States) the time ball that has descended each year at the New Year's Eve celebration on Times Square). Local 137 members have also produced signs, billboards, and banners for well-known New York City locations such as Yankee Stadium and Kennedy Airport, and worked on the restoration of several New York City landmarks, including the Apollo Theater and Nathan's Famous Hotdogs. Members have also worked in the New York City metropolitan area, as far afield as New Jersey. The collapse in 1970 of the Broadway Central Hotel, in which the Local's offices were located, destroyed some of its earliest records. The Local purchased its own building in Woodside, Queens, in 1983.
Local 137 members are required to complete a five-year apprenticeship training program that offered by the Local.
Presidents of the Local have included Moe Rosen, Bernard Friedlander, Martin Fruchter, William Fotiadis, and Paul Collins, Jr.
Arrangement
Contents of collection has been arranged by archivist in boxes by topic.
Bibliographical Note
Information for this guide was drawn from "Ordinary People, Extraordinary Lives--Labor History in New York City," by Janet Wells Greene, from the March 2000 issue of Annotation (newsletter of the National Historical Publications and Records Commission); "The Sign Industry of New York City," senior thesis by Bernard Friedlander, Empire State Labor College, New York, undated; "Sheet Metal Workers Local 137--A Century of Sign Making," Louis M. Brill, SignWeb (online companion to Signs of the Times), posted June 7, 2010; The Sheet Metal Workers' Story: A Chronicle of Fine Craftsmanship 1888 - 1980, Arch A. Mercey, Merkle Press, Glen Dale, Maryland, 1980; "Sheet Metal Workers' International Association Local # 137," Claudia Hommel, New York City Labor Records Survey (LRS#292), 1985.
Metal workers |x Labor unions |z United States.; Black-and-white photographs.; Fruchter, Martin; Fotiadis, William; Rosen, Morris, 1896-1962; Collins, Paul, Jr.; ArtKraft Strauss; Friedlander, Bernard; Sheet Metal Workers' International Association. Local 137
- Executive Board Minutes, Art Kraft Strauss Attendance Cards and Membership dues Records, 1973-1986 (Box 1A, Box 1b, Box 11)
- Button Collection - William Fotiadis, Campaign Literature - William Fotiadis, Testimonial Dinner Program - Moe Rosen, Correspondence and Contracts (alphabetical by company), 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Contracts, 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
- Apprentice Record, 1969-1989 (Box 4)
- General Correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box 4)
- General Correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box 5)
- New Jersey Local 172, undated (Box 6)
- Tenney Engineering (Local 28): Plant Closing, 1991, undated (Box 7)
- Apprenticeship Records Local 137 - Recruitment and Training Local 172-28 Correspondence and Contracts, undated (Box 8)
- Local 172-28 Correspondence and Contracts, undated (Box 9)
- Local 172-28 Correspondence and Contracts, Moe Rosen photographs, undated (Box 10)
- Certificate of Incorporation for Sheet Metal Workers Sick and Benevolent Association of New York, from State of New York, 1916 (Box MS003, Folder 1)
- Photographs, circa 1930s-1950s (Box A005, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Note
  Five black and white photographs, including an undated group portrait shot outside "the Marble Shop" in the Bronx, group shots of Local 137 members on the job, at a demonstration, and at a conference.
- Archived Websites, Mar 11, 2009-ongoing
  The mission of the Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local Union No. 137 is to organize, educate, and represent all workers in associated crafts in the New York region. The purpose of the Union is to represent all members in their fight to improve benefits, wages, and safe working conditions. The website contains event listings, a blog, images from events, and information on their apprenticeship program. In 2014, the Sheet Metal Workers International Association officially merged with United Transportation Union.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.